Eleanor Estes Papers
© 2007 University of Connecticut
Eleanor Estes Papers.
undated, 1900-1988.
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center.
Estes, Eleanor (Rosenfeld).
10.05 linear feet.
MSS19970049
The collection contains professional and personal correspondence, photographs, drafts, essays, newspaper clippings and ephemera related to Estes long career as a children's book author and illustrator.
Biography
Eleanor Estes ( 1906-1988 ) was the author and illustrator of a number of children's books over her long career. Born in West Haven, Connecticut, Estes worked as a librarian at the New Haven Public Library before winning a scholarship to the Pratt Institute in Brooklyn, NY, where she met her husband. She worked as a children's librarian for the New York Public Library until her first book was published in 1941. That book, The Moffats, set in fictional Cranbury, Connecticut, was based on Estes' own childhood in West Haven. She was the recipient of the Newbury Medal in 1952 for Ginger Pye.
Published Works
The Moffats, Harcourt, Brace and Company, 1941. Dodd Boyson 5604, Boyson 2518, Levy E2809, Levy E4064, CLC C1536.
The Middle Moffat, Harcourt, Brace and Company, 1942. Dodd Levy E2123, CLC B206, CLC B130.
The Sun and the Wind and Mr. Todd, Harcourt, Brace and Company, 1943. Dodd CLC C538.
Rufus M., Harcourt, Brace and Company, 1943. Dodd Levy E2124, CLC A611.
The Hundred Dresses, Harcourt, Brace and Company, 1944. Dodd Boyson 2253, Boyson 2476, Boyson 4326, CLC B142, CLC B537.
The Echoing Green, Macmillan, 1947
The Sleeping Giant and Other Stories, Harcourt, Brace, 1948. Dodd Boyson 2475.
Ginger Pye, Harcourt, Brace, 1951. Dodd CLC B536, CLC B141.
A Little Oven, Harcourt, Brace, 1955.
Pinky Pye, Harcourt, Brace and World, 1958. Dodd CLC A1673.
The Witch Family, Harcourt Brace, 1960. Dodd Levy E34.
The Alley, Harcourt, Brace and World, 1964. Dodd Levy B59.
The Lollipop Princess, Harcourt, Brace and World, 1967. Dodd CLC C358.
Miranda the Great, Harcourt, Brace and World, 1967. Dodd CLC A1052.
The Tunnel of Hugsy Goode, Harcourt Brace Jovanovich, 1971.
The Coat-Hanger Christmas Tree, Atheneum, 1973.
The Lost Umbrella of Kim Chu, Atheneum, 1978.
The Moffat Museum, Harcourt Brace Jovanovich, 1983.
The Curious Adventures of Jimmy McGee, Harcourt Brace Jovanovich, 1987.
Scope and Content
The Eleanor Estes papers contains professional and personal correspondence, speeches, essays, drafts and proofs, photographs and ephemera related to Estes long career as a children's book author and illustrator.
Arrangement
Series I: Professional Correspondence ( undated, 1938-1987 ) includes all correspondence related to Estes' career as an author, illustrator and public speaker. All correspondence is organized by sender and is organized into a number of subseries based around the three major publishing houses with which Estes was affiliated. Subseries A: Harcourt correspondence, Subseries B: Macmillan correspondence, Subseries C: Atheneum correspondence, Subseries D: Miller Brody correspondence, Subseries E: Cricket, Subseries F: General professional correspondence.
Series II: Personal Correspondence ( undated, 1900-1989 ) contains all mail not directly related to Estes' major publishing efforts. Subseries A: Personal Correspondence, Subseries B: Postcards, Subseries C: Fanmail
Series III: Written Materials and Related Writings ( undated, 1946-1984 )
Series IV: Photographs ( undated, 1948-1986 ) is separated into two subseries. Subseries A: Photographs Separated From Correspondence, Subseries B: General Photographs.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to children's literature and associated artwork. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Separated Material
The following materials have been separated from the collection and cataloged:
Dodd Call No.
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Family Names:
Ardizzone, Edward.; Bulla, Clyde Robert.; Graham, Margaret Bloy.; Griffith, Ann Warren.; McElderry, Margaret.; Slobodkin, Louis.; Titzell, Anne Parrish.; Waugh, Alexander.
Places:
Connecticut--Fiction.; Los Angeles (Calif.); New Haven (Conn.); New York (N.Y.); West Haven (Conn.)
Subjects:
Children’s literature.
Document Types:
Photographs.; Correspondence.; Proofs.
Occupations:
Authors, American.; Illustrators.; Librarians.
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Acquisition Information
The collection was donated by Helena Estes in 1997.
Detailed Description
- Series I: Professional Correspondence, undated, 1923-1987
  - A. Harcourt, Brace and Company, 1926-1987
    - 1926-1927 (Box 1:, Folder 16)
    - 1944 (Box 1:, Folder 1)
    - 1945 (Box 1:, Folder 2)
    - 1946 January - March (Box 1:, Folder 3)
    - 1946 April - June (Box 1:, Folder 4)
    - 1946 July - September (Box 1:, Folder 5)
    - 1946 October - December (Box 1:, Folder 6)
    - 1947 January - March (Box 1:, Folder 7)
    - 1947 April - June (Box 1:, Folder 8)
    - 1947 July - September (Box 1:, Folder 9)
    - 1947 October - December (Box 1:, Folder 10)
    - 1948 January - March (Box 1:, Folder 11)
    - 1948 April - June (Box 1:, Folder 12)
    - 1948 July - September (Box 1:, Folder 13)
    - 1948 October - December (Box 1:, Folder 14)
    - 1949 January - March (Box 1:, Folder 15)
    - 1949 July - September (Box 1:, Folder 17)
    - 1949 October - December (Box 1:, Folder 18)
    - 1950 January - March (Box 1:, Folder 19)
    - 1950 April - June (Box 1:, Folder 20)
    - 1950 July - September (Box 1:, Folder 21)
    - 1950 October - December (Box 1:, Folder 22)
    - 1951 January - March (Box 1:, Folder 23)
    - 1951 April - June (Box 1:, Folder 24)
    - 1951 July - September (Box 1:, Folder 25)
    - 1951 October - December (Box 1:, Folder 26)
    - 1952 January - March (Box 1:, Folder 27)
    - 1952 April - June (Box 1:, Folder 28)
    - 1952 Julty - Septmber (Box 1:, Folder 29)
    - 1952 October - December (Box 1:, Folder 30)
    - 1953 January - March (Box 2:, Folder 31)
    - 1953 April - June (Box 2:, Folder 32)
    - 1953 July - December (Box 2:, Folder 33)
    - 1954 January - March (Box 2:, Folder 34)
    - 1954 April - June (Box 2:, Folder 35)
    - 1954 July - September (Box 2:, Folder 36)
    - 1954 October - December (Box 2:, Folder 37)
    - 1955 January - March (Box 2:, Folder 38)
    - 1955 April - June (Box 2:, Folder 39)
    - 1955 September - December (Box 2:, Folder 40)
    - 1956 (Box 2:, Folder 41)
    - 1957 (Box 2:, Folder 42)
    - 1958 (Box 2:, Folder 43)
    - 1959 (Box 2:, Folder 44)
    - 1960 (Box 2:, Folder 45)
    - 1961 (Box 2:, Folder 46)
    - 1962 January - June (Box 2:, Folder 47)
    - 1962 July - September (Box 2:, Folder 48)
    - 1962 October - December (Box 2:, Folder 49)
    - 1963 (Box 3:, Folder 50)
    - 1964 (Box 3:, Folder 51)
    - 1965 (Box 3:, Folder 52)
    - 1966 (Box 3:, Folder 53)
    - 1967 (Box 3:, Folder 54)
    - 1968 (Box 3:, Folder 55)
    - 1969 (Box 2:, Folder 56)
    - 1970 (Box 2:, Folder 57)
    - 1971 January - June (Box 3:, Folder 58)
    - 1971 July - December (Box 3:, Folder 59)
    - 1972 (Box 3:, Folder 60)
    - 1973 (Box 3:, Folder 61)
    - 1974 (Box 3:, Folder 62)
    - 1974 (Box 4:, Folder 76)
    - 1975 (Box 3:, Folder 63)
    - 1976 (Box 3:, Folder 64)
    - 1977 (Box 3:, Folder 65)
    - 1978 (Box 3:, Folder 66)
    - 1979 (Box 3:, Folder 67)
    - 1980 (Box 3:, Folder 68)
    - 1981 (Box 3:, Folder 69)
    - 1982 (Box 4:, Folder 70)
    - 1983 (Box 4:, Folder 71)
    - 1984 (Box 4:, Folder 72)
    - 1985 (Box 4:, Folder 73)
    - 1986 (Box 4:, Folder 74)
    - 1987 January - May (Box 4:, Folder 75)
  - B. Macmillan and Company, 1945-1952, 1957-1958, 1987
    - 1945-1946 (Box 5:, Folder 77)
    - 1947 (Box 5:, Folder 78)
    - 1948 (Box 5:, Folder 79)
    - 1949 (Box 5:, Folder 80)
    - 1950-1952 (Box 5:, Folder 81)
    - 1957 (Box 5:, Folder 82)
    - 1958 (Box 5:, Folder 83)
    - 1987 (Box 5:, Folder 84)
  - C. Atheneum, undated, 1971-1986
    - undated (Box 6:, Folder 85)
    - 1971 (Box 6:, Folder 86)
    - 1973 (Box 6:, Folder 88)
    - 1974 (Box 6:, Folder 89)
    - 1975 (Box 6:, Folder 90)
    - 1976 (Box 6:, Folder 91)
    - 1977 (Box 6:, Folder 92)
    - 1978 (Box 6:, Folder 93)
    - 1979 (Box 6:, Folder 94)
    - 1980 (Box 6:, Folder 95)
    - 1981 (Box 6:, Folder 96)
    - 1983 (Box 6:, Folder 97)
    - 1984 (Box 6:, Folder 98)
    - 1986 (Box 6:, Folder 99)
  - D. Miller-Brody, undated, 1973-1977
    - undated, 1973 (Box 7:, Folder 100)
    - 1974-1977 (Box 7:, Folder 101)
  - E. Cricket, undated, 1972-1987
    - undated, 1972-1987 (Box 7:, Folder 102)
  - F. General Professional, undated, 1948-1987
    - undated, 1948-1949 (Box 7:, Folder 103)
    - 1950-1958 (Box 7:, Folder 104)
    - 1960-1968 (Box 7:, Folder 105)
    - 1974-1979 (Box 7:, Folder 106)
    - 1980-1987 (Box 7:, Folder 107)
- Series II: Personal Correspondence, undated, 1900-1989
  - A. Personal, undated, 1934-1988
    - Bishop (Hawkins), undated, 1978-1982 (Box 8:, Folder 108)
    - Breeds, undated, 1978 (Box 8:, Folder 109)
    - Briggs, undated, 1948-1982 (Box 8:, Folder 110)
    - Buckley, 1985-1988 (Box 8:, Folder 111)
    - Coleman, 1936-1977 (Box 8:, Folder 112)
    - Cookinham, undated, 1959-1987 (Box 8:, Folder 113)
    - Crossgrove, undated, 1964-1966 (Box 8:, Folder 114)
    - Crossgrove, 1967-1981 (Box 8:, Folder 115)
    - Didier, undated, 1951-1982 (Box 8:, Folder 116)
    - Duncalfe, undated, 1970-1987 (Box 8:, Folder 117)
    - Duncan, 1978-1980 (Box 8:, Folder 118)
    - Easton (Hurwitz), 1955-1987 (Box 8:, Folder 119)
    - Griffith, undated, 1948-1949 (Box 8:, Folder 120)
    - Griffith, 1950-1982 (Box 8:, Folder 121)
    - Hough (Taylor), undated, 1986-1987 (Box 8:, Folder 122)
    - Johnson, undated, 1948-1987 (Box 8:, Folder 123)
    - Kerlan Collection, 1967-1988 (Box 9:, Folder 124)
    - LaGuardia, undated, 1934-1970 (Box 9:, Folder 125)
    - Massey (Bedell), undated, 1948-1978 (Box 9:, Folder 126)
    - McElderry, undated, 1948-1971 (Box 9:, Folder 127)
    - McKenzie, undated, 1944-1986 (Box 9:, Folder 128)
    - O'Neall, 1948-1978 (Box 9:, Folder 129)
    - Patton, undated, 1970-1983 (Box 9:, Folder 130)
    - Sektberg, undated, 1948-1981 (Box 9:, Folder 131)
    - Shaller, 1986-1987 (Box 9:, Folder 132)
    - Thomas, 1933-1957 (Box 9:, Folder 133)
    - Wentworth, 1948-1986 (Box 9:, Folder 134)
    - General
      - undated (Box 10:, Folder 135)
      - 1934-1941 (Box 10:, Folder 136)
      - 1948 July - August (Box 10:, Folder 137)
      - 1948 September - December (Box 10:, Folder 138)
      - 1949-1951 (Box 10:, Folder 139)
      - 1952 (Box 10:, Folder 140)
      - 1953-1969 (Box 10:, Folder 141)
      - 1970-1972 (Box 11:, Folder 142)
      - 1973-1979 (Box 11:, Folder 143)
      - 1980s, 1980 (Box 11:, Folder 144)
      - 1981 (Box 11:, Folder 145)
      - 1982-1984 (Box 11:, Folder 146)
      - 1986 (Box 11:, Folder 147)
      - 1987-1988 (Box 11:, Folder 148)
  - B. Postcards, undated, 1900-1989
    - Blank, undated (Box 12:, Folder 149-150)
    - Unidentified, undated, 1900-1939 (Box 12:, Folder 151)
    - Briggs, 1930-1969 (Box 13:, Folder 152)
    - Calhoun, 1955-1959 (Box 13:, Folder 153)
    - Estes, undated (Box 13:, Folder 154)
    - Estes, 1910-1939 (Box 13:, Folder 155)
    - Estes, 1940-1949 (Box 13:, Folder 156)
    - Estes, 1950-1959 (Box 13:, Folder 157)
    - Estes, 1950-1959 (Box 13:, Folder 158)
    - Estes, 1950-1959 (Box 13:, Folder 159)
    - Estes, 1960-1969 (Box 13:, Folder 160)
    - Estes, 1960-1969 (Box 13:, Folder 161)
    - Estes, 1960-1969 (Box 13:, Folder 162)
    - Estes, 1970-1979 (Box 14:, Folder 163)
    - Estes, 1970-1979 (Box 14:, Folder 164)
    - Estes, 1970-1979 (Box 14:, Folder 165)
    - Estes, 1970-1979 (Box 14:, Folder 166)
    - Estes, 1970-1979 (Box 14:, Folder 167)
    - Estes, 1980-1989 (Box 14:, Folder 168)
    - Gaston, 1900-1910 (Box 14:, Folder 169)
    - Haeseler, 1970-1979 (Box 14:, Folder 170)
    - LaGuardia, 1970-1979 (Box 14:, Folder 171)
    - Rosenfeld, 1920-1969 (Box 14:, Folder 172)
    - Smith, 1900-1910 (Box 14:, Folder 173)
  - C. Fanmail, undated, 1948-1987
    - undated, 1948-1958 (Box 15:, Folder 174)
    - 1962-1968 (Box 15:, Folder 175)
    - 1970s, 1970-1972 (Box 15:, Folder 176)
    - 1973 (Box 15:, Folder 177)
    - 1974-1979 (Box 15:, Folder 178)
    - 1980s, 1980-1984 (Box 15:, Folder 179)
    - 1985 (Box 15:, Folder 232)
    - 1986 (Box 15:, Folder 180)
    - 1987 (Box 15:, Folder 181)
- Series III: Unpublished Written Materials and Related Writings, undated, 1946-1984
  - Articles authored by Estes, 1952-1971 (Box 15:, Folder 182)
  - Articles about/interviews with Estes, undated, 1953-1974 (Box 15:, Folder 183)
  - "Pre-Moffat Notes,", undated (Box 16:, Folder 184)
    Notes from the period of Estes' recovery from tuberculosis.
    - Notes, undated (Box 21:, Folder 233)
    - Notes, undated (Box 21:, Folder 234)
    - Notes, undated (Box 21:, Folder 235)
    - Notebook, undated (Box 21:, Folder 236)
    - Notebook, undated (Box 21:, Folder 237)
    - Notes, undated (Box 21:, Folder 238)
  - "The Doll's Hospital", undated (Box 21:, Folder 239)
  - "The Fallen Acrobat", undated (Box 21:, Folder 240)
  - "The Two Cent Mask", undated (Box 21:, Folder 240)
  - Notes and revisions, The Echoing Green, circa 1946 (Box 16:, Folder 185)
  - Proofs, The Sleeping Giant, circa 1947 (Box 16:, Folder 186)
  - Notes written in L.A., 1949 (Box 21:, Folder 241)
  - "The Four Nervous People", 1949 (Box 21:, Folder 242)
  - Notes on Miranda the Great, circa 1967 (Box 16:, Folder 187)
  - Working draft and final draft of The Lollipop Princess, circa 1967 (Box 21:, Folder 243)
  - "Outside my door in Brooklyn," 2 copies, 1977 (Box 21:, Folder 244)
  - Draft, Chapter One of The Moffat Museum, with revisions, 1984 (Box 16:, Folder 188)
  - Unused draft, Chapter Five of The Moffat Museum, "The Room Outside,", [1984] (Box 16:, Folder 189)
  - Entry in The Dictionary of American Biography, 1983 (Box 16:, Folder 190)
  - Unidentified speech notes, undated (Box 16:, Folder 191)
  - Newbery acceptance speech draft, 1952 (Box 21:, Folder 245)
  - Speech, Washington, D.C., circa 1953 (Box 16:, Folder 192)
  - Speech, Baltimore Museum of Art, 1954 (Box 16:, Folder 193)
  - Speech, Ontario Library Association, 1956 (Box 16:, Folder 194)
  - Speech, Bridgeport, 1958 (Box 16:, Folder 195)
  - Speech, Brooklyn College, 1958 (Box 16:, Folder 196)
  - Speech, Philadelphia, 1958 (Box 16:, Folder 197)
  - Speech, North Babylon, NY, 1961 (Box 21:, Folder 246)
  - Speech, Bucknell University, 1966 (Box 16:, Folder 198)
  - Speech, Onondaga Library, 1967 (Box 16:, Folder 199)
  - Speech, Providence, 1967 (Box 16:, Folder 200)
  - Speech, Albertus Magnus, 1973 (Box 16:, Folder 201)
  - Speech, New Haven Public Library, 1973 (Box 16:, Folder 202)
  - Book reviews, 1948-1975 (Box 16:, Folder 203)
  - Book reviews, 1978-1987 (Box 16:, Folder 204)
  - Publicity materials, undated, 1973 (Box 16:, Folder 205)
- Series IV: Photographs, undated, 1948-1986
  - A. Photographs Separated From Correspondence, 1948-1986
    - Japanese children and doll festival, 3 prints, 1948 (Box 17:, Folder 206)
    - Three unidentified Japanese children, 1948 (Box 17:, Folder 207)
    - Estes display, Maryland State Teachers Association Teacher Librarian Division, 2 prints, 1952 October 17 (Box 17:, Folder 208)
    - Crossgrove children, 5 prints, 1962-1963 (Box 17:, Folder 209)
    - Gloucester City Library Moffat celebration, 1968 (Box 17:, Folder 210)
    - Gladys Gould, 1973 (Box 17:, Folder 211)
    - Ann Coleman in Greece, [1977 December] (Box 17:, Folder 212)
    - Des Plains, IL, student holding The Lollipop Princess, 1980 (Box 17:, Folder 213)
    - James, Cindy and Chad Cookinham, [1980 March 19] (Box 17:, Folder 214)
    - Chad Cookinham, 1981 (Box 17:, Folder 215)
    - Patton graves, 4 prints, 1983 (Box 17:, Folder 216)
    - Mary, Scott and Christina LeRoy, Gil Patton, 7 prints, [1983 August 23] (Box 17:, Folder 217)
    - Eleanor Estes Day at West Haven Public Library, 1983 November 17 (Box 17:, Folder 218)
    - Gillian Buckley as Jane Moffat, 4 prints, 1985 (Box 17:, Folder 219)
    - Walton School, Eleanor Estes Month, 1986 (Box 17:, Folder 220)
  - B. General photographs, undated, 1961-1985
    - Tetsura and Mitsuya Watanabe, undated (Box 17:, Folder 221)
    - Helena and Eleanor Estes, undated (Box 17:, Folder 222)
    - [Ann?], 1961 (Box 17:, Folder 223)
    - Susan Hurwitz, 1962 (Box 17:, Folder 224)
    - Crossgrove children, 5 prints, 1962-1963 (Box 17:, Folder 225)
    - Mrs. T. Hamlin Briggs and California Poppies, April 1966 (Box 17:, Folder 226)
    - Eleanor Estes and Margaret McElderry, 1966 (Box 17:, Folder 227)
    - Crossgrove Christmas card, 1978 (Box 17:, Folder 228)
    - Susan Easton and Eleanor Estes, 1985 July 5 (Box 17:, Folder 229)
- Series V: Ephemera and Artifacts, undated, 1946-1988
  - Newspaper clippings, undated, 1949-1988 (Box 18:, Folder 230)
  - Unidentified writings, undated, 1946 (Box 18:, Folder 231)
  - Programs and invitations, undated, 1948-1986 (Box 18:, Folder 232)
  - Matted portrait of Estes, undated (Box 19)
  - Index cards of Estes foreign editions, undated (Box 19)
  - Printing plate from The Echoing Green, 1948 (Box 19)
  - Cassette tape of Carolyn Patton's funeral, 1983 (Box 19)
  - Eleanor Estes Day Proclamation, City of West Haven, 1983 November 17 (Box 19)
  - Cassette tape letter from R.H. Curtiss, 1984 (Box 19)
    Dictated letter from Curtiss on New Haven trolleys and steam fire engines
  - Hundred Dresses scroll, undated (Box 20)